Preliminary Inventory to the Tasker H. Bliss papers, 1918-1919
Hoover Institution Archives
Tasker H. Bliss papers,
1918-1919
XX339
Bliss, Tasker H.
1 folder (0.1 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence and memoranda, relating to the American Commission to Negotiate Peace at the Paris Peace Conference; the military, economic, and political situation in Europe following World War I; and European relief and reconstruction. Includes correspondence with Herbert Hoover.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection open for research.
Access Points
Hoover, Herbert, 1874-1964.; Paris Peace Conference (1919-1920); International relief.; Reconstruction (1914-1939)--Europe.; World War, 1914-1918.; World War, 1914-1918--Civilian relief.; World War, 1914-1918--Peace.; Europe.; United States--Foreign relations.; United States--Armed Forces.
Biography
General, U.S. Army; chief of staff, 1917; delegate, Paris Peace Conference, 1918-1919.
Container List
- Herbert Hoover to Tasker H. Bliss, 1918 December 1. Returns memorandum from Major Lawrence Martin to Tasker H. Bliss re steps to be taken regarding fuel shortage in Europe (missing) (Folder 1)
- Tasker H. Bliss to Herbert Hoover, 1918 December 30. Assumes paper received from Lewis Strauss is the memorandum discussed at the conference on December 29, 1918, and he is in agreement with the points stated; believes that strong, direct appeal to get Woodrow Wilson to push for relaxation in the blockade against the Central Powers is desirable
- Lewis Strauss to Tasker H. Bliss, 1918 December 30. Sends report, by direction of Herbert Hoover, re nutritional conditions in Germany (report is attached to original of this letter in the Tasker H. Bliss Papers in the Library of Congress)
- Lewis Strauss to Tasker H. Bliss, 1918 December 30. Sends memorandum, by direction of Herbert Hoover (enclosure missing; may be in the Tasker H. Bliss Papers in the Library of Congress)
- Herbert Hoover to Tasker H. Bliss, 1918 December 31. Asks if Major Poillon could be transferred to Food Service within the next few weeks
- W. B. Wallace to Lewis Strauss, 1918 December 31. Gives thanks to Herbert Hoover for Nutritional Report on Germany
- Lewis Strauss to Tasker H. Bliss, 1919 January 3. Sends documents, by direction of Herbert Hoover: 1. provisional draft of memorandum on blockade (enclosure missing); 2. copy of Herbert Hoover's letter to British Food Controller J. R. Clines (attached); 3. copy of Herbert Hoover's letter to the British Ministry of Food (enclosure missing). Missing enclosures 1 and 3 may be in the Tasker H. Bliss Papers in Library of Congress
- Tasker H. Bliss to Herbert Hoover, 1919 January 10. Re securing services of Col. Poillon
- Herbert Hoover to Tasker H. Bliss, 1919 January 11. Thanks him for letter of January 10; realizes the value of Col. Poillon's services to Tasker H. Bliss
- Herbert Hoover to Tasker H. Bliss, 1919 February 19. Sends memorandum re problem of Armistice and needs guidance from the Peace Commission (enclosure is attached to the original memorandum in the Tasker H. Bliss Papers in the Library of Congress and is entitled "Relief of Liberated Peoples")
- Tasker H. Bliss to the American Peace Commission, 1919 February 26. Asserts that the U.S. should make it clear it will not offer future military and financial aid to European nations after the signing of the peace with Germany; believes this will be a deterrent to future aggressive moves by Allied Nations in Europe
- Herbert Hoover to Tasker H. Bliss, 1919 February 27. Sends extracts from correspondence, telegrams, and reports from Trieste, re problem of Italians delaying food shipments to Vienna and Prague (enclosure, "Extracts from Letters, Minutes, and Cabled Reports on Subject of Transportation Difficulties at Trieste," is in the Tasker H. Bliss Papers in the Library of Congress)
- Tasker H. Bliss to Herbert Hoover, 1919 February 28. Thanks him for his letter of February 27 with enclosures
- Tasker H. Bliss to Herbert Hoover, 1919 March 10. Encloses copy of memorandum submitted to the American Commissioners re Art. VIII of Armistice (surrender of the German merchant fleet); Mr. Lansing and Major James Brown Scott agree with these terms)
- Herbert Hoover to Tasker H. Bliss, 1919 March 12. Sends copy of his letter of March 12 to Italian Food Controller S. Crespi, re shipment of foodstuff from Trieste
- Tasker H. Bliss to Herbert Hoover, 1919 March 27. Tells of report received from General Harries, compiled by two medical officers who accompanied a prisoner of war train from Germany to Romania; suggests shortage of rolling stock (railroad) is due to disorganization and not to lack of material
- J. D. Ellis to Tasker H. Bliss, 1919 April 2. Encloses copy of wireless from Lt. Grove in Warsaw (enclosure missing; may be in the Tasker H. Bliss Papers in the Library of Congress)
- Hugh Gibson (?) to Tasker H. Bliss, 1919 March 29. Sends copy of the letter of March 29 from Herbert Hoover to Woodrow Wilson, discussing bolshevism and problems involved in the establishment of a Relief Commission to feed Russia
- Herbert Hoover to Tasker H. Bliss, 1919 April 5. Thanks him for the invitation; has seen Admiral Niblack
- Herbert Hoover to Tasker H. Bliss, 1919 April 14. Encloses copy of his letter of April 14 to Woodrow Wilson (enclosure to the latter letter, a report entitled "Supreme Economic Council," is attached to the original letter in the Tasker H. Bliss Papers in the Library of Congress)
- Tasker H. Bliss to Herbert Hoover, 1919 April 15. Thanks him for the copy of the March statement re relief measures
- Herbert Hoover to Tasker H. Bliss, 1919 April 21. Sends report of April 11 by Capt. Joseph C. Green in Bucharest. (enclosure, "ARA Mission to Romania" by Joseph C. Green, is attached to the original letter in the Tasker H. Bliss Papers in the Library of Congress)
- Herbert Hoover to Tasker H. Bliss, 1919 May 14. Encloses statement showing foodstuff delivered by ARA to German-Austria in first months of 1919 (enclosure is attached to the original letter in the Tasker H. Bliss Papers in the Library of Congress)
- Herbert Hoover to Tasker H. Bliss, 1919 May 16. Encloses copy of cable - a version of Russian reply to Nansen letter; does not differ materially from text intercepted by the French (enclosure attached to original letter is in the Tasker H. Bliss Papers in the Library of Congress)
- Herbert Hoover to Tasker H. Bliss, 1919 May 16. Encloses two-page memorandum by Herbert Hoover, "Another Plan for the Financial Rehabilitation of Europe")
- Herbert Hoover to Tasker H. Bliss, 1919 May 17. Encloses his statement of May 15, 1919, to the Supreme Economic Council, showing total relief effected during the month of April
- Tasker H. Bliss to Herbert Hoover, 1919 May 22. Acknowledges receipt of a number of letters from Herbert Hoover; thinks Herbert Hoover's financial rehabilitation plan is interesting and wants to learn Herbert Hoover's views re lifting blockade in Hungary
- Unknown to Tasker H. Bliss, 1919 June 24. Encloses report, by direction of Herbert Hoover, indicating progress of relief measures for May, and total supplies furnished to European countries from Dec 1 to May 30 (the report, dated 1919 June 2, is from Herbert Hoover to the Supreme Economic Council)
- Herbert Hoover to Tasker H. Bliss, 1919 June 24. Encloses copy of telegram of June 22 from Captain Hanrahan to Herbert Hoover, reporting serious turn in Danzig when Peace terms signed; Herbert Hoover agrees with Capt. Hanrahan that 500 men should be sent to protect millions in goods stored in Danzig)
- Hanrahan to Herbert Hoover, 1919 June 25. States there is no immediate worry re Danzig, but difficult to foretell because of day to day change)
- Tasker H. Bliss to Herbert Hoover, 1919 June 25. Re possibility of Allied forces occupying Danzig if local police is unable to handle the situation
- Herbert Hoover to Tasker H. Bliss, 1919 June 27. Abstracts report of June 24 from Col. Groome in Libau, re detention of Lieutenants Nixon and Harrington
- Herbert Hoover to Tasker H. Bliss, 1919 June 28. Herbert Hoover dinner called off, since Woodrow Wilson is leaving and many officials will be seeing him off
- Herbert Hoover to Tasker H. Bliss, 1919 July 1. Reports that Lieutenants Nixon and Harrington have reached Riga; Colonel Groome is sending report of incident to Herbert Hoover, who will forward it to Tasker H. Bliss
- B. Bakhmeteff to Tasker H. Bliss, 1919 July 8. Memo re U.S. aid to anti-Bolsheviks in the Baltic Area
- Henry James to White and Tasker H. Bliss, 1919 July 17 ("Memorandum Concerning Possible Action At Budapest")
- T. R. Ryan to Tasker H. Bliss, 1919 July 23. Re wave of militarism in Poland
- Tasker H. Bliss to Herbert Hoover, 1919 July 23. Encloses copy of letter of July 21 from Marshall Foch to Tasker H. Bliss, re arrest of Lieutenants Nixon and Harrington
- Gibbes Lykes to Tasker H. Bliss, 1919 July 26. Encloses additional dispatches (enclosures missing)
- Unknown to Tasker H. Bliss, 1919 August 1. Re exchange of Polish potatoes for German coal and steel
- Unknown to Colonel Wallace, 1919 August 4. Encloses information desired by Colonel Wallace (enclosures missing)
- Unknown to Colonel Wallace, 1919 August 5. At Herbert Hoover's direction, encloses copy of telegram from Captain Gregory, and copy of telegram from Lieutenant-Colonel Romanetti to Clemenceau (enclosures missing)
- Herbert Hoover to Tasker H. Bliss, 1919 August 7. Re needed personnel for Colonel W. N. Haskell's staff in Armenia
- W. M. G. Atwood to Tasker H. Bliss, 1919 August 9. Re materials being shipped to Serbian Government via Italy
- W. M. G. Atwood to Tasker H. Bliss, 1919 August 9. Encloses copies of telegrams received from Lieutenant Colonel Causey in Budapest (enclosures missing)
- W. M. G. Atwood to Tasker H. Bliss, 1919 August 12. Re rail blockade against Serbia
- W. M. G. Atwood to Tasker H. Bliss, 1919 August 14. Encloses copy of a letter from Colonel Causey (enclosure missing)
- W. M. G. Atwood to Tasker H. Bliss, 1919 August 25. Encloses copy of report of August 4 from Captain Patterson to Colonel Causey, re disturbances in Trieste (enclosures missing)